hello everybody thanks for joining again
I'm excited to introduce my conversation
with David fuller who is the co-founder
of the channel rebel wisdom and before I
give some more context around that a few
housekeeping things so links below for
all of my offerings through the
circlings Institute just my company we
are doing everything online right now so
it's a real good opportunity if you've
been thinking about it but have been
limited to be able to get to San
Francisco to come and participate in
circling and learn more about that we
have a Thursday night open event where
anyone is welcome it's a three-hour
drop-in event so the links below it's
best to get the info off the Facebook
page which is provided below also if
you're interested in working with me one
on one go ahead and email me and I think
that's it for now so this is a really
great conversation it's been it been
quite a while it seems like last summer
last time I talked to David
however one of the things I really
appreciated in the conversation was a
lot of things kind of coming together I
think for David and for myself a deeper
understanding about what rebel wisdom
and David in particular is really doing
I'm on multiple levels and with his
channel and his work and the choices
that they've made there and because
David comes from in particular this is
the thing I really appreciate it was
that David comes from a more of a
traditional media background an NBC in
BBC and he's an example kind of a rare
example of someone who was deeply in
that world very ethnically and has
transitioned into out of the mainstream
social media into whatever this is that
were watching right now still yet to be
defined however him bringing a lot of
those sensibilities to bear in a real
positive way and being a witness to a
chicken to the change in media as a
whole but from inside of it so we got
into we got into a lot of that and what
that was like for him and examples were
that is happening in other places and
people that isn't happening and it's a
really enlightening conversation so I
really enjoyed it a lot and um we we
talked about a video where he he had
watched recently that I think he had he
had done right when they started the
channel so I'll include a link for that
below so you can watch that where he
listened to what he thought the future
was about that channel and what they
were up to and whatever a year over a
year later he watches it again and
realizes that his
he's right in the middle of what he
thought was coming so it has that this
conversation has that glimmer of
emergent intelligibility kind of crackle
a few times so it was really great so uh
hope to do it again with him soon
enjoy
hello David hey guy we just hit the
record button yeah so we were just
talking about your everything is has
slowed down or locked down around you
but rebel wisdom is is that this is
cooking you're busier than you've ever
been
yeah yeah I sort of see people on
Facebook talking about how they're kind
of bored and they've watched everything
on Netflix and they're not sure what to
do next and what happens when life gets
back to normal and friend of mine posted
something like what habits from the
lockdown are you gonna carry on when you
get back to normal and bleep saying I'm
gonna make more space in my life and
mm-hmm that's not my reality and hasn't
been since I guess kind of it's the same
for my friend back in journalism as well
right there when the news ramps up
they're very very busy but that's what I
found since the beginning of this is not
enough hours in the day to do all of the
things that need to be done and just an
expansion on every level of become the
business effectively the rebel wisdom so
there's the film's we've done of a
couple of big online events in some ways
it's kind of focused us a lot more
clearly because we were doing some
in-person events and some online events
but it's been very clear it's like no
you know you're in which side of it
which side of the fence are you on on
that one
like it or not it's I mean the end
person the in-person events certainly
the festival last year in the festival
this year was going to be a sort of high
point so the fact that we've had to
bring that online yeah feels a sense
yeah there's a disappointment that there
are lots of people who are going to be
flying in from around the world who
we've been connecting with on
for many months and that was going to be
a big event potentially up to like 300
400 people in London right so the fact
that that's not happening is
disappointing right but at the same time
I actually feel the focus that comes
from knowing that all of the energy is
now going into online building online
community is actually quite good mm-hmm
yes there was all this sort of
difficulty of trying to be but Oh could
we run retreat so we really value like
we know that there's something you can
do in person you can't do online yeah
we'd always been sort of split between
well do we do more in-person retrieves
what do we do more online community in
the fact that we've we've had that
option taken away it makes things a bit
clearer I think yeah totally I mean
we're kind of going through something as
well
like I I put up doing all this stuff
online all of my courses and stuff like
that online for as long as possible and
then of course this happened and it just
forced us into it now we're realizing
like it's very difficult to not it's it
that I mean that's interesting in itself
just the fact of how easy it is to be
online right and like how practical it
is on so many different levels yeah but
it works actually it's funny I was I'm
surprised with working with groups and
stuff like that that it actually works
pretty pretty well like surprisingly
well so it works but I'm with you about
there's nothing like you know a roomful
of people
like getting into it like there's
nothing like the the oxytocin and all
the serotonin and all the dopamine that
gets going in that space that's there's
nothing like that for sure you know it
the last time last time we talked I
think you had just gotten back from
Burning Man mmm and and one of the
things that struck me about that
conversation was
[Music]
was how much you were kind of in the
process of kind of finding what you were
doing is you were doing it yeah I mean
you were it's almost like I got the
sense of what you're up to with the
rebel wisdom that you were in some sense
authoring it hmm however you weren't
clear exactly your role in the
authorship right that it was like a
literally a conversation that you were
having and it sounds like it sounds like
when I've when I've heard you speak
lately it's it sounds like it's it's
it's turned a little bit more you're
more clear about the direction that
you're going and it's not at least what
I'm hearing words to you know update me
with this but it sounds like you've
really turned a corner in terms of of
taking on practice and providing a space
for the practice of the psycho
technologies and all the things that
have been talking about is that is that
true how do you see how do you see
yourself now when rebel wisdom yeah I
guess the we did a big free one-day
event the on the faith and that was was
called resilience and sense-making and
it had kind of a framing at the
beginning with Jamie wheel and Dan Marsh
Oh Hamilton talking about like the
bigger picture and then we after that we
did lots of breakouts with practices of
about I think each and we have three
breakout running at the same time
they're up to about 100 people that need
to break out each time sub breakouts
within those doing different practices
mm-hmm inquiry to breath work to
movement and that felt very it's
probably the the first time that we've
done an event that really felt like he
jailed quite as well like we had the we
had the sense making we had the kind of
big picture intellectual content but
then we also drew a very clear line to
well if you want to make sense well you
have to
the work yeah want to be resilient part
of being resilient is understanding
what's going on maybe understanding what
the deeper shifts are that we're seeing
like if this is the end of the old
system and it's gonna feel like a death
in a lot of ways understanding what that
might mean kind of systematically and
intellectually is going to help us feel
a bit more grounded and resilient but
then there's also the work of yeah Wow
how do i how do I feel about this yeah
how do I give voice to that and to go
through the processes like this sort of
senses and the other thing as well since
the beginning of this crisis I looked
back at the film that we made two years
ago to sort of say what is rebel wisdom
and it all fits with what's happening
right now like I watched it I made that
film and yet when I watched it again I
watched it almost with new eyes like it
says at the beginning this is the
descent we're going through the
breakdown of the old system and
everything that we've been doing with
rebel wisdom since the beginning has
been like suddenly I am recopy that I've
written which before probably only a few
people in this kind of there wasn't
really a good name for the met aware of
the sense making way of the sort of the
kind of people that I know you are in
dialog with as well you've been saying
wow we're in a meaning crisis we're in
some kind of a real systemic crisis and
that's going to unfold now I think
that's becoming really clear to everyone
yeah yeah totally so I think maybe you
feel the same but just this sense of
since the beginning of this crisis just
this deep sense of alignment and focus
and purpose has been just like this
absolutely kind of solid core of this is
exactly what we've been preparing for
and tracking on some level since since
the beginning of rebel wisdom and
probably since kind of my
background before I came into before I
created rebel wisdom like this was this
was and we're now in a in a time where
the news what the updates of the news
needs that deeper level like
understanding systems thinking
understanding complexity understanding
you can't actually make sense of even
the day-to-day right now without some of
those deeper lenses yeah and then maybe
you even need to go back to like the
mythopoetic lens of what is the kind of
this as Jordan wall I know you've been
in dialog with quite a bit talks about
there's some there's some knowledge that
is so important but so rarely used and
we store it in the mythopoetic layer
yeah yeah they're in deepest stories
it's the sort of thing that we may only
need once every couple of generations or
once every millennium that's where we
store it that's why those store that's
what we have those stories and that's
why they resonates so deeply is that
this is going to come in useful sometime
yeah so there's the sense of those of us
whose been who've been looking at the
world through that kind of deeper
mythopoetic layer this is when the
rubber meets the road and so many of the
people that I've been talking to and
even in the the rebel wisdom community
are group calls they've just been the
sense of like focus and per person like
so many people saying yes this is these
are the times I was built for this is
what I've been preparing for without
realizing it for the last however many
years so there's the sense and then when
I look back at some of the material that
we've put out on rebel wisdom I look I
think wow just look so prescient right
now yeah all of these people that I've
been interviewing and like these these
incredible thinkers packing what they've
been saying it's like yeah there's
there's a sense that many of us have
been sensing this and in some ways
feeling like okay this this was going to
happen yeah yeah yeah literally you've
been sensing it and responding to it
right and so it sounds like you had a
kissed so when you looked at
is that is that the glitch in the matrix
which which film is that that you're
talking about that you watched of oh I'm
talking about actually the two and a
half minute film that was it's cool
what is rebel wisdom there is literally
just there okay very short clips and I
we can maybe put it in the show notes
for anyone watching who wants to see it
I'd be really really interesting yeah
because it's gonna be thing what you do
what you're doing because it's it's you
could look at the way that you've been
talking about what you've been doing and
your future and then come back and look
at it and then compare notes and I mean
even that is a that's a trip yeah I mean
that itself is like a way of making like
a way of making sense and honing
yourself up it's like a feedback loop
that's really quick and then the
feedback that you're getting from your
pro cuz now that you have participants
right you don't just have audiences but
you have participants right and you're
getting up back and it's a very
interesting you're in a really unusual
it seems to me a really unusual position
it's all for me to say whether it's
unusual it's quite usual for me now that
the this sense of I was thinking about
as we were gonna have this conversation
I was thinking about you know your
history is within mainstream media right
like he worked with NBC and BB slap yeah
mostly Channel 4 News
I was in the Channel 4 News room so that
in in in those institutions right it's
it's interesting because I've been
watching I've been I've been putting on
like the NBC Nightly News mm-hm and you
know the the music comes on and breaking
news today and you know all of them and
it hits all those anchors from when I
was a kid
this this experience of of like
everything would stop when I was a kid
when when dan Rather would come on right
and like in everyone good would go right
there would be something like there were
no questions about what we were watching
and it was so almost ritualistic yeah
and I noticed that liked it although it
hit all those it hits all those anchors
for me
I remember those but when I look at that
thing I'm like it's so clear that
something else is happening than what I
thought was happening back then it's
just like those main the mainstream
media is breaking down at such a level
and changing so deeply it's just you get
the sense that they don't know where
they are however it's been the
institutions that have grounded us right
in so many ways and so it's really
interesting to think about like when I
was thinking about you having to some
degree been in that world and then
coming out of that world in some ways
you're an example of you know is I think
it is it done is it Jordan Hall talks
about that is like that that's all part
of the blue church right and and that
what's the next one after that is there
another we talked about the insurgency
being the red religion yeah so the blue
church I mean I think it's a very very
useful frame the blue church being the
institution of not just the media but
also the whole institution of like
top-down hierarchy and the deep state
and all of them academia so Harvard all
of these systems that were designed to
to organize the world after the Second
World War and the baby they were very
effective but they also left out certain
viewpoints certain perspectives and that
was what fueled the insurgency in the
red religion and then sort of bubbled up
with prom
and brexit what was left out of the blue
church synthesis right I mean that's
what my first film was about what sort
of the glitch in the matrix was exactly
that these what are these perspectives
that are not being reflected in them in
the system that we have which is
affecting the reality is far too complex
to be contained within any low
resolution model yeah and I'd say that
the blue church model was actually
fairly high resolution but it's still
not enough and there are certain values
and certain perspectives that are not
included also that there's a kind of it
becomes corrupt or it becomes corrupt
possibly not the right word but it's
certainly become yeah the right word
it's sort of atrophies a little bit like
that trophy's as time goes by yeah yeah
and that yeah I guess I mean I'm that's
why I'm most fascinated by I think is
this sort of tension between the
alternative in the mainstream yeah and
also concerned by because this is a film
that I'm making at the moment about sort
of the growth of conspiracy theory and
and all of these kind of alternative
narratives around Ovid which seemed to
be just proliferating and you're seeing
people who have never sort of shared a
conspiracy theory before sharing stuff
and there's a very complex picture
because a lot because some of what
people say is conspiracy theory is
actually like I'm not saying that
everything that's not like an extreme
narrative is conspiracy theory because
some of the mainstream narrative
themselves are partial and but then
you've got what concerns me is you've
got the situation where we had
gatekeepers before I won't perfect but
at least we had some gatekeepers and
there were some very good values held in
those gatekeepers yeah but I
internalized as a journalist you know
like report something you need to check
it factually you need to you need to get
people's responses if you're going to
put any allegations you need to get the
response of where you make
the allegation about the other and there
were enforcement of those especially in
the UK we've got off we've got a very
different media landscape than the US
but there are genuine checks and
balances I feel like we've gone from one
place where there were the gatekeepers
and they there are obviously flaws in
that system but at least there was some
sense of objective truth right into a
world and I can imagine that you go
through this kind of on through the
valley of kind of the alternative media
and we may end up with only most of the
crowd thoughts decentralized way of
checking truth claims and but we're not
there yet
and we're in this very dangerous place
in between one structure and another and
right now we're in a place where it
feels like a very dangerous time in a in
a in a very dangerous time yeah yeah
we've got the tech giants now making
these decisions and they're doing in a
very sort of haphazard way but they're
because they're also benefiting from
like conspiracy stuff or missing let's
cook the same misinformation rather
conspiracy missing information can be
very viral ready and they're only really
interested in maximizing time on-site
maximizing shareability of content so
they've been there not more into towards
truth yeah we've got this very dangerous
moment when we've got actors who are not
oriented towards truth and though we've
got all of these kind of other actors
including state actors like Russia and
China and who are and we've got very few
checks and balances and it seems that
we've been overwhelmed yeah that for me
is very very concerning is that yeah I
don't see I hear like Jordan Jordan Hall
formerly Jordan green wall I think his
narrative is is brilliant about
decentralized media and broadcast and I
also and he talks about kind of the
death of the blue church but it's almost
in there inevitably going towards more
and more decentralized and then the
destruction of
like the New York Times the all of the
institutions academia all of these
things are losing their power and it's
like I get that but that terrifies me
but the valley
yeah the valley that we have to cross to
some other way of making sense unless
we're all the idea that we all have to
individually check absolutely everything
and we all have to rely on a discernment
while that feels empowering on some
level it's also it's not possible we all
proxy our sense making somewhere to
something we do we can't avoid it that's
how we exist as as you humans we have to
connect brands and so it's like this
feels like yeah it feels very very well
I think that more than anything like the
information landscape and the the lack
of faith in any authorities who I mean
to be fair they've done an awful lot to
lose that trust I'm not defending the
existing authorities but the fact that
we haven't had no trusted sources
anymore and cannot even really imagine
what a trusted source would look like
who would be heard and respected on both
sides of the political divide or all
sides of the blizzard but you mentioned
dan Rather before like that kind of
figure of someone who is trusted by
everyone I can't even imagine what that
would look like right now
great great he hasn't was a long rap but
it's son yeah well one of the things you
said is yeah as a journalist coming from
that side of the street like you've
internalized right certain ethics so
that was something that that actually
like you still you still have that right
hmm like you still have that yeah my
client would like to say something there
because I think like journalists there
are values held within turn like good
journalism journalistic ethics that I
think I'm very
we can't lose those like a lot of people
are very down on journalism and I agree
with a lot of the criticisms by
journalism as far too easily captured by
groupthink it's captured by corporate
interests is captured by a lot of these
a lot of these are the factor
but but if you break down what
journalism should be about kind of good
treatment of information yeah they're
really valuable things they're valuable
practices and they're valuable
values and the practices like I've seen
I've been tracking like the the the
intellectual darkweb for example yeah
which is for people who maybe don't know
is is a kind of loose conglomeration of
podcasts and alternative media figures
and I've seen them go through this
process of real world learning that they
have to have these values you saw it
with someone like Joe Rogan who's the
biggest podcaster in the world he he
went through this process with he had
Jack Dorsey the head of Twitter on his
podcast and it was a crappy interview
Jack Dorsey just basically stonewalled
everything and just was and Joe after
was kind of like yeah it was a crappy
interview but his audience just turned
on him in a way that you've never
experienced before because they were
like you didn't hold him to account you
Twitter have been censoring people
they've been banning people you didn't
and Joe was like whoa I just get people
on to my I just built the show by
getting on people I want to talk to and
having a conversation with them and
suddenly my audience is yeah me a
traitor calling me a sellout calling me
a shill for not asking Jack Dorsey in
holding into account all of these topics
and Joe you saw him go through this
really that's what I really respect
about Joe Rogan is that he went through
this process of self analysis and like
water I didn't ask for this job but now
I'm being expected to do this job yeah
and he he did he did the interview Jack
Dorsey again and got on a journalist Tim
Paul to to basically have a go at Jack
Dorsey so he did but he was learning
effectively that he was a journalist
without realising he had certain
abilities to his audience that he never
asked for I think a lot of people in the
alternative media space are learning the
it reach comes with responsibilities
okay you have a certain number of if
you've got a few million subscribers
there are different responsibilities to
that in the mainstream media
Eric Weinstein talks about this really
well he says a lot of the people in the
old media inherited their positions yeah
so then the journalists themselves they
don't have a lot of reach but the New
York Times has a lot of reach they've
inherited their positions and he thinks
that they probably have a different
responsibility too
yes someone who's built their platform
by hand or their Twitter account by hand
there probably is a different set of
responsibilities but if you've got two
hundred thousand a million followers I
think you do have a certain set of
responsibilities mm-hmm they're very
different but what we're seeing right
now with coronavirus and misinformation
is that everyone in the same way that
you could affect someone as you go out
like you're not just keeping your safe
self from the virus you're keeping other
people safe from the virus and not
becoming a vector I think everyone is
now getting a visceral understanding of
that you can also be a vector for
misinformation yeah yeah if we're
realizing that I think we are then we're
also realizing that some people are much
more toxic vectors for information than
others mm-hmm yeah I think this is
something we're learning very quickly
right now you know it's an interesting
you know it's an interesting time when
when being a journalist ISM anamur is an
emergent property lega Rogan it emerged
for him that he's a journalist he's
finding his his way which is really I
think one of the thing that's
interesting is like who is the audience
in this world right so what one of the
things I've had this thought about about
you know watching Peterson was and I get
that people have different opinions
about this but like I mean I like I mean
I like him I mean I just have a lot of
respect for like how he would just walk
I don't know if he was if he knew who he
was talking to and he was talking but he
used to walk in and he
would just confront the hypocrisy right
he would even couldn't and he wouldn't
any you would just stay to the truth
that it was a great example of that but
one of the things that I think was
started to happen at least in my view at
the end sometimes right was actually
something that he used to talk about in
his in his class when he would talk
about that Hitler right was it just he
didn't come out like Hitler and then
insert something on the world no like
there was there was an evolution where
certain things he would say he would get
like a cheer and so on some level not
even like it's the conscious level but
just in in the dance of co-creating you
know Germany and and Hitler co-created
each other at that that time and I was
actually kind of watching as time went
on like he it seemed to me that he
talked a lot more his audience got
really like against the post-modernism
right against those people right and he
got a lot of a lot of applause for that
and he just it occurred to me that he
started he started taking the language
of more and more polarization in a way
that I think that that was very similar
to that same dynamic right so he had a
real cult following and I don't think
he's I'm not calling him Hitler or
anything like that but there's a dynamic
that there's a Co shaping what's going
on right and so you just gave an example
of where that went really well
right with a reasonably well with Hogan
right where he has his interview he's
just doing his thing right and then he
gets he starts to get but he but that
was a conscious thing that he confronted
and made adjustments around and maybe
sees himself differently through that
like that's really is this like that
that in itself is just an interesting
thing that you could that can just
happen or emerge for you yeah
there's an interesting dynamic that's
coming up or thinking about as you're
talking which is the idea of
antifragility which is that more
conflict makes us stronger and there
seems to be a parallel there in terms of
does criticism do we shrink under
criticism and just retreat into I know
best and this person's wrong and I don't
know why they're saying that anyway or
do we actually are we able to grow into
criticism and and that is something
again just referring back to the
intellectual dark web you saw very
different trajectories between Joe Rogan
and Dave Rubin Dave Rubin I've been high
I've done an interview with him where I
was I was quite challenging and he one
thing I think it's fairly are
non-controversial to say the one thing
debut is not very good that was taking
criticism he does seem to have a pretty
strong narcissistic edge and he even on
like he's been he's very very
thin-skinned yeah and it's interesting
because he's talked about I mean even
took her over and talked about how he
was kind of he hinted that he was sort
of mentally not particularly
did he say something like attract to be
pretty done it's a kind of stupidity
that comes from there's a kind of
stability that comes from not being able
to take criticism that is that means
that you get stuck yeah and that I've
noticed quite a lot since I've sort of
get more into personal growth like
there's a type of stupidity that is just
lack of fabric cognitive ability that
people have more or less of but there's
a there's a certain there's a certain
type of intelligence that just comes
from being able to grow in terms of
criticism openness yeah and challenge
that I see with someone like Joe Rogan
and actually it makes Joe Rogan a a
really intelligent interviewer and a
really like he you'd be the first to say
he's not a philosopher is no he's not a
particularly deep thinker but he's
naturally a very very very
interviewer because he's constantly
growing and he's constantly learning and
he's also got a very good sense for what
and someone is getting stuck in
certainty and you see like his some of
his interviews he's actually picking up
very intuitively when someone doesn't
know what they're talking about because
he can kind of sense into what their
great kind of speaking from a very fixed
position or they're all they're open
just quite gently yeah you know there's
there's something in the no view of you
like there's almost two different types
of intelligence there there's and
becoming fixated in a person in a
position means that you stop growing
I mean I'm aware of where that is yeah
you can happen at any point like that's
another another really interesting point
is that we don't know like when we're in
a relationship with someone and it's
growing and we just get us too much of a
call wound maybe all right I can't go
beyond there right now right
I don't accept that responsibility of
the dynamic of water mine here yeah in
so many relationships it's great I mean
if anything it's a great it's it's
interesting I've never quite looked at
it from the lens of that that dynamic
actually affecting a certain kind of
intelligence or or acuity right a
perception but that makes sense it's
like if there's uh if we call it a kind
of narcissism where where my ideology or
my way of thinking is so wrapped up with
who I need to see myself as right and
therefore if that's the case I'll only
be around people and talk with people
that are will mirror that to me so it's
not it's not it's not a knowledge it's
not a knowledge that I'm learning it's a
knowledge I'm imposing getting mirrored
yeah and if if I open up if if if I am
that image and I need its reflection if
I open up the criticism right if I'm
really identified I can't tolerate it
right so I'll make it or make them wrong
or avoid them or something like that and
then just be around the people
that will you know concur with me and
yeah you're right like there's that's a
very different thing whereas what it
takes to actually open up the conflict
and the criticism and to exposure and to
take criticism it it's well that's
character mmm let's character it's like
being able to go through something
difficult that you don't understand and
then lean into it and take a look and
adjust and that interaction or that
conversation seems to be what makes our
character seems yeah it is character but
it's also infinitely more difficult to
do that if we have a public persona or
we have a public profile you know that
seems to be very very difficult you to
do yeah as we get identified with
certain perspectives and admitting that
we're wrong in public and even even just
the sheer data
overwhelm of however many people telling
us that we're great and maybe some
people telling us that we're not and
we've then got we've got an infinite
amount of perspectives and it's very
easy to sort of select only the ones
that tell us that we're great and yeah
more everyone else like that
it's not something I have a suspicion of
just becoming really famous almost it's
almost impossible not to have that
feedback loop disrupted quite
fundamentally yeah yeah what's
interesting I'm wondering about so it
seemed like when we said when he started
when you brought up the thing about the
like the intelligence aspect right or
rolling right yeah totally
and there's a kind of a peninsula did
the conversation shifted right we're
like both like oh there's something
things that we've thought about however
in
in the dialog something came up and now
that there's kind of like there's almost
a sense of like we're bringing things
together and articulating them in new
ways so to me that is whatever that is
and and being able to have these
conversations this is I guess is what
you would call sense making right what
John and I had been talking a lot about
is like dial logos right
not just dialogue like relating but
actually where we we encounter a place
where all of a sudden we start to learn
more than the sum of the two of us knew
right so that's one of the things I've
just been like fighting myself zeroing
in on on what I'm doing with with with
I'm still finding out what I'm doing
right in terms of these videos and stuff
but I'm I'm wondering about like it's
sent to me it sounds like from the
wouldn't you say that like your
inclination to do the the practice work
with people right I wouldn't you say
that a lot of that practice work is
precisely about being able to open up to
the other tolerate ambiguity tell the
truth and stay with what's happening and
make sense of it as it happens yeah yeah
that's very much yeah that's very much
that the skill set that I've been
learning so I did a counseling training
based around inquiry so inquiry I know
that you each almost like kind of based
nebulous but I mean it sort of feels
like it has the same origin as something
yeah it's not exactly cigarette
basically dialogue and so kind of trying
to get to the edge of our understanding
and find new words for things and what I
found I didn't really put this together
and I don't know whether we talked about
it before but it maybe not because I
think this was a real eyes
and I had relatively recently which is
that by so the counseling training I did
was based around inquiry so we were
doing an awful lot of that yeah
sense of like following the thread of
our unfolding experience and learning
something new about ourselves in
dialogue with someone else and circling
around particular topics and really
integrating that kind of way of yeah
that way of understanding and then what
I realized was oh that's exactly what
was fueling rebel wisdom what was
fueling the exploration was okay what's
the and they sort of sense of Jordan
Pederson being the first like really
emergent thing of like whoa this is
really interesting
yeah just you're the Petersons I got I
found when I first discovered Jordan
Pederson in 2017 I knew immediately this
is going this is the thing this is the
thing that we need that the world needs
to hear right now like the deeper
mythological and not the anti woke start
from the really kind of anti pomo
material although I think that was that
there was mean there was signal there
for sure but it was more like the deep
mythopoetic
of a culture someone arguing for the the
truth of the religious experience at and
psychedelics and all these things in the
public arena as the most high-profile
intellectual that's an extraordinary
thing yeah and so following so that was
the first like okay this emergent thing
and then reflecting on that phenomenon
that then erupted on your show that I
used to work on for ten years which is
like okay pull that one together yeah
the whole conversation I had the Jordan
Pederson when I went to see him in
Toronto was about synchronicity and then
he explodes on Channel 4 News
yeah with Kathy Newman who I used to
work with yeah yeah many years it's like
okay make sense of that synchronicity
and then following the thread of okay
following that sense that okay what is
the emergent thing right now I think
that took me on to the likes of Jordan
Hall Jamie wheel mm-hmm Mountain burger
and many other systems thinkers whose
rid what's the real cutting edge of the
conversation and the intellectual dark
web as well and I've also made it I'm
also going to put a link to a gave a
talk about the intellectual dark webbing
in New York to a university where I kind
of like that that sense of the emergent
with the intellectual dart live I think
ended quite soon after it was named yeah
yeah but then I look around at some of
the people that we're also good friends
with I'm sure that we we know many of
the same people people who are practiced
in this kind of psycho technology also
seem to be attracted to some of the same
conversations yeah like once you develop
this as a tool yeah in yourself yeah I
think you then start to be able to track
what is new and emergent and the culture
as well totally so there's really
something about like just as you're
talking about it when you said yeah I
knew what Jordan Peterson that this is
this is this is worth or a pulsus right
and he just went towards it before that
right before that like in your life
hmm what were you up to like what were
you doing before you saw that and and
your attention went with Jordan Peterson
in the beginning of all of this what who
were you what were you doing why why did
you exist what was happening so
immediately before I was very passionate
about men's work and we still some of
the so we treat we teach retreats and
transformational work and we still up
until this code situation we're doing
men's retreats I'm very passionate about
that
and before that I've been sort of while
I was at Channel 4 News I'm doing a lot
of foreign affairs and the Arab Spring
and then left to do documentaries mostly
about foreign affairs and also I was
also very interested in okay I pinched a
few documentaries that never really got
made about more spiritual topics I was
also interested in the the the nexus
between spirituality and mental illness
that was something I've always been
interested in growth
Stanislav Grof we maybe people might be
familiar with he talked about spiritual
emergencies and just this sense of I was
always interested in what are the one of
the areas of culture where a more
expansive conception of humanity is
pushing through so for me some of those
areas were psychedelic therapy so I get
the first piece about psychedelic
therapy back in 2008 on mainstream TV in
the UK
who's got MDMA therapy and results for
the shown that it worked very well yeah
like why is the psychedelic experience
so therapeutically valuable that for me
shows like how narrow the kind of
reductive reductionist conception of
people of the person is from kind of
materialistic medicine you know that's
one one area yeah other area is the sort
of idea of spiritual emergencies and
just the like psychiatry is an absolute
car crash as far as I'm concerned what
we have no we have no like yeah we're
dealing with complex systems like the
psyche I think we're going to look back
and say that what we would do what we've
been doing with drugs in the 20th
century 21st century's medieval might
we'll look at it as how we how
tried to treat people with leeches back
in the Middle Ages you just do not
understand the psyche we do not
understand the self-healing nature of
the psyche we do not understand like the
DSM that whole that whole paradigm of
[Laughter]
what sometimes gets very amorphous the
idea of paradigm shift yeah where's
being from when I study philosophy I've
always had this sort of sense of what
the new paradigm looks like and then I
think together with having sort of home
the idea honed a sense of where the
conversation is I think that's my that's
that's my solution that's where what my
background has allowed me like being in
a newsroom for 10 15 years and just
getting a sense of where the
conversation is where it gets stuck
where the sort of gatekeepers are of
certain ways of sort of seeing
conversation or where it needs to shift
to and how it why it gets stuck in
certain place I think that's what what I
got from that experience of being in a
newsroom right well it sounds like it's
I think what I'm hearing you say it's
interesting
um it's fractal in a little bit about
that we talked about with you know it's
interesting because it sounds like the
figure one of the figures in the
intellectual dark web right that then
you're like this went this dis did not
go he did not go in the right direction
right he's exemplifying it was with was
David Rubin right and you had a
interview with them but he stood out for
you as doing something different right
then what you that what you were you had
your eye on right and then we got to a
conversation about like another an
opposite example of that is Joe Rogan
right who just you know comedian just
having his friends on got really popular
and then the guy from Twitter comes on
and he's censoring it and then his whole
fan base kind of turned on him a bit
and then he juror ovens used to being
punched in the face that's the main
difference
yeah you've linked it to John reveille
keys idea about embodied by different
forms of knowledge yeah joe rogan is a
very embodied oh yeah he's very embodied
thinker and he's he's an MMA fighter and
commentator and I think like genuinely I
think he thinks much more with his whole
body yeah
his is used to being like he's not
easily knocked off center yeah and he's
also really relational right yeah really
relational like fight it's interesting
to think about formal fighting is I mean
you kind of you have a love affair
oftentimes with the guys that you spar
with right there's a real deep rapport
to be able to be vulnerable love to try
to kill you right there's a there's a
camaraderie there that I think that I
remember in my own kind of sport my
background in sports it's very it's
there is a deep a deep kind of
relationality there but there's but
there's a way that he responded that
really struck you as the light kind of
like the light side which was he didn't
back into his corner and defend himself
he he actually opened up and he he's
like well this is not what I was doing
maybe I need to take on the
responsibility because it's here because
maybe now I'm a journalist now right and
he's and then he had him back on and and
then he then you were they you were
tracking him being able to track
conversations which have a little bit
more of that gatekeeper quality or not
gatekeeper but the the thing that you
internalized from from being a
journalist of a certain amount of facts
like you started to notice his bullshit
indicator started to and in his own way
he started to highlight that so if
you're tracking all of that right and
what's interesting is when you talked
about what I really heard it when you
when you talked about before before
rebel wisdom you had tried to try to do
documentaries abroad in con spirituality
right and
and psychiatry right the intersections
between those two things
and it sounds like I would imagine that
you just couldn't get the the credit the
media that at the time was just not what
was going I'm not gonna do this was it
did you get turned down a lot on a lot
of projects er yeah I mean the windows
for those kind of yeah it's very
difficult to get something that is going
against the dominant narrative yeah
because you can always like for example
with something if you're going to talk
about the links between spiritual
experience and mental illness for
example then you've got to face the
argument that are you telling people
that they should stop taking their
medication and that is a hugely
dangerous thing to be putting out there
we're not going to be responsible for
that kind of argument okay that sort of
thing it's very difficult when there is
an openness now I think to a lot of
conversations and also there's some
truth in that you've got to be careful
well you gotta be careful with those
kind of arguments you you you can't say
I think a lot of a lot of people in in
sort of psychologists and people in the
medical system are aware whether the
strong and materialist
paradigm that you're you're what's going
on is just brain chemistry and it has no
meaning to what's going on in your life
that's not there are not many people we
really think that most people are
actually in some kind of a understanding
that obviously your life experiences
influence you in some way but they're
also operating within a paradigm that is
pretty much reliant on drugs yes
and nothing else yes yes very like those
overworked doctors will prescribe you
antidepressants almost immediately and
will not prescribe you talking therapies
to understand what's going on in your
life or yeah so you're you're fighting
certain you're fighting against a very
well-defined
hmm system which has then huge financial
interests which has huge yeah inertia in
a certain direction I mean there are all
of these different factors involved
right what and one of the things that I
just want to highlight what what looks
fractal to me right like a through line
that I'm hearing I think I'm hearing
with you as
he's like even there you were noticing
you were noticing okay here's something
that's scientific ray psychology and
they're addressing things in the name of
science that are missing this whole
other world right that can't be deduced
scientifically let's say so you and
what's interesting is that you had both
the gatekeeper and the like the sensing
at the peripheries and you didn't just
go well let's go let's go deeper into
the science and deny all of that you
actually wanted to bring them together
you wanted to bring them into into
conversation so there's a there's a way
in which what I'm hearing is is the
internalization of like know what's
reality here what's actually factual but
there's also you're also saying that
it's also factual right or it may be
factual that there's a whole other
reality that you can't look at in terms
of facts in the same way and if you do
right it'll become pathology like it
will become pathology there's a there's
a way in which there's a there's a like
a true align that I'm hearing through
all of that that is
I'm just appreciating because I see you
and what you guys are doing a rebel
wisdom is is is an example of mainstream
shifting into this new thing right and
you're really conscious of this you know
what you know what it's like to be in
mainstream media you know the
sensibilities right and you're also
conscious of how it's working just as
demonstrated in this conversation you're
tracking people you're like like you're
just you have a pulse on it but you're
also part of the you're part of the
shift an example of shift and noticing
the shift right so it's as I just see
you as somebody just really on the
periphery of something self-conscious of
self-conscious of what you're doing
growing personally like I would imagine
well first of all how does that sound
that's my that's my recap of what I'm
what I'm basically hearing is if there's
actually been a through line that you're
not just you're not just like what are
the facts but you're also noticing
what is something what so there are
worlds that disclose that can't be
disclosed just through facts right and
and that we need to open up these two
worlds and have them comfort like in
conversations in it and I think you're
aware of the dangers of any of that
stuff becoming a kind of an ideologies
that people just believe right um and
there's a sweet spot there yeah this
kind of tendency to impress themselves
upon you and whatever happens I mean I
keep coming back to Ken Wilbur's model
of sort of the four quadrants of
knowledge most I think I think he was
essentially right in a lot of the
particulars of his morals and so in in
that in that sense than fact really only
well they they occupy two two quadrants
but they're not the whole thing and I
think that's really it's a really useful
model to make sense of the world and to
understand that there are yeah there are
certain things about reality that
irreducible yeah
and yet we built a world on very few of
the yeah we built a world that
emphasizes the material and the
quantifiable and that's yeah it's not
enough yeah totally it's not enough and
yeah you're actually really grounded in
those things and you've been bringing
those worlds together
right yeah and slightly and wait what's
your pet like when you just look at you
right like you yourself and being a
person and watching your own you know
because there's that sense of like you
know Boober talks about I thou you
spoken is one word right there's an eye
that it rises this a little bit we were
talking about earlier
an eye that arises with your audience
right there's I though I'm a different
eye in some respects than I am with you
than I am with somebody else there's
like a Acco rising who's the eye that
arises with has been arising with rebel
wisdom like me have you seen many kind
of shifts and you're like just
personally being you and when you're
walking around and looking at trees and
the way you're responding to your
relationships and your family and what's
the like have you've seen differences in
your own your own convert of your own
intimate conversation with yourself in
your world in a way like I've been so
single focused and busy over the last
two years of doing the wisdom I don't
really have that much yeah I feel like
in many ways my world is kind of it's
certainly expanded in terms of the
people that I'm talking to and
conversations I'm having mostly online
but yeah not so much
you know I don't feel like I had time to
sort of stop and feeling to whether
things are fundamentally shifting in
terms of who I am I mean I guess I feel
more more sort of confident and aligned
in my purpose and my answers yeah
direction and that does feel like a sort
of very physical thing this was a
visceral thing yeah yeah I noticed these
cities you sat back to answer that
question I appreciated that hmm yeah and
like when he said when he said yeah I
actually haven't had much time to even
kind of sit back and check that out but
like when you just do
when you just do I would just imagine
like on I think the thing I wanted just
to acknowledge is is just the
intelligibility that has been on a pulse
and it has been deeply absorbed in and
adjusting and responding to something
that's been really what I'm hearing is
true and true for you probably for a
long time right mm-hmm and so I really
appreciate I just appreciate that I
appreciate all the adjustments that
you're making but I also really do think
my sense is you do occupy a very rare
position right in in that you are you
are of both worlds right while being
interested in what's happening and
having a meadow awareness of like
there's some shift happening and you are
the one who is the one who's been
shifting and having that conversation I
just noticed in my conversation with you
I like I wanna I want to get though I
want to get that talking because you do
you do occupy I think a really rare
position and I appreciate that about you
yeah I think that's right I don't know
many people from Channel 4 News who
don't think I've gone just gonna say
what what what who are you to them now
like if you have a general sense of it
like are you crazy are you like renegade
are you what how do they talk about you
when well because of the cat because of
the glitch in the matrix film that was
critical of channel 4 and Kathy Newman I
haven't heard from many of them for a
very long time
no and I knew putting that out would
create that reaction yeah I was mindful
I mean it wasn't attacking them but like
it wasn't attacking them too much but I
knew that would end my career with them
and with probably with the sort of
mainstream more generally may have heard
from somebody came to one of our events
said
he mentioned that he was coming to our
event and someone said oh he's a guy's
band from channel 4 actually ban from
ITN I should say we're interested which
is he made telephone use very
interesting so what's that like for you
um yeah I feel a bit misunderstood
mm-hmm and I do wonder whether there's
anyone there he kind of
recognizes what I was kind of I was
trying to say hey I don't know yeah have
you reached out to any of them any of
them really
not really
okay I've got a couple of friends still
there who I sometimes send story ideas
and stuff to write what what do you
think would happen if you reached out to
them and just started to have the
conversation with them about what that
was like for them or or started to
bridge like bring some of them on your
show or go over there
like it's it just I feel kind of tent I
feel kind of tender mmm
something tender and me happens like as
we're talking about that well it's
difficult because they I mean who would
that be
they've got responsibilities they've got
it would be difficult to have an open
public conversation about it because
they wouldn't want to go that they
didn't want to go there with the I was
trying to broker a conversation between
Cathy and Jordan after the interview
blew up and they didn't want to go there
then so they want to go there now right
right
well you said when he said I really felt
that a couple of things it's like I felt
I felt that when you said yeah I I don't
remember exactly what you said but I
basically I I feel a bit misunderstood
mmm all of that right and I I think
there's I think why I felt contender
there is like listening to you is just
actually to what degree actually you
have internalized so much of the values
of that world that are really still I
can tell they're deeply it's about a
deep integrity right and so you are
really being deeply Integris to yourself
here and then and then the people that
use a lot of the people that you shared
that with any history right you are no
longer talking with you or when you've
reached out they go I just feel a
loneliness there somehow like a
loneliness or is that does that feel
correct or just something something
there that's it's just deeper
yeah yeah I mean I do I guess I do feel
misunderstood by you know there's a part
of me always I guess that sort of thinks
I wonder if any of my former colleagues
ever watch some of the stuff that I put
out especially recently and think
actually this is worthwhile and the sort
of stuff that we should be doing right
right cities hearing yourself hearing
yourself to say that
what's that what's that like
you frozen oh yeah you back yeah totally
I thought you froze well you know I just
know I'm just noticing that I have an
urge to I'm like I am urge to bring that
world in your world into conversation
and dialogue I just that would be really
really interesting well there is a
conversation that needs to happen like
we are in touch with people who want to
bring some of the stuff that we've been
talking about into into government I
think this is the kind of time for like
the deeper systemic thinking and the the
idea of paradigm shift like people are
willing to have those kind of
conversations while it's most clear that
a lot of the old ways of breaking down
so that is a sense of theirs that's an
ongoing conversation like how do we
bring these worlds back together yeah
yeah
yeah interesting it's just I just I
think I'm just appreciating how personal
it is for you
of course like you're you're like you
you're venturing off into new work
you're breaking new ground right and
where you came from a lot of the people
you probably really looked up to and had
deep relationships with at least
professionally you're out here and you
don't know whether or not they actually
see right they see what you're doing is
valid right and in just the reckoning
the reckoning of that the reckoning of
that I would imagine it would be a
little bit I wish I were you anyways I
would I would personally be kind of
confronted to go back and ask them right
cuz cuz that's on some level if I looked
up to them right like I wouldn't want I
wouldn't I do willing to but it wouldn't
look real comfortable to open myself up
to my own self doubt that would be
triggered in all of that you know yeah
this is a sense of you know people who
I've respected and also people with
quite a kind of big public profile if
you're kind of watching people like Jon
Snow or Krishnan guru-murthy who British
people will know you know oh that they
probably think that you've gone
completely mental
yes the only it's like a lot it's
aligned is syncing to so I just I think
I think what I'm actually realizing it's
like one of the things that I'm
I know that for me in my own way since I
started doing these conversations it's
kind of taken off a life of its own but
there really is a particular quality of
vulnerability that comes with this like
that's hard to describe and I think it's
it's just that have knowing that there's
people who are watching you that you
don't have a relationship with that are
informed by you in ways that you don't
quite totally know about right and so
it's just been strange too it's it's a
strange vulnerability to meet people who
know a lot about you that you don't know
anything about them that's a really
weird that's a strange no it strikes me
as a so we're done where it's a weird
dynamic right but there is a I do feel
the sense of that there is a
responsibility there as well right to
understand where they're coming from and
like listen to them and like there's
there's um here I can I can really sit
can really kind of get that sense of
that that like oh yeah I am
on some level my identity isn't just
over here it's a conversation that's
happening with right it's a it's a back
and forth because I know that for me and
I think there's a lot of people you
could probably relate to this as well
it's like you know you start following
people online right over a period of
time and you kind of walk around with
them right you think about what they
were saying like you whole arguments and
tensions that they're holding and then
you see the world through those things
and then you watch the next video and
the next conversation and it's a it's a
they start to become guests in your
psyche if you will that become really
really integrated right so to be one of
those people on some level or to be in
your case in a lot of case providing
access to those people on some level you
you know we we are being hosted you know
in people's nervous systems and and
levels that that they're not even aware
of so it's it's
just an it's an unusual position to be
in and there is a vulnerability to it
and I think it's like for you to there's
there's even more of one because you
come from you come from a background
that's that's in many ways you're like
in many ways you you're you're moving
out of and towards the new thing right
that like so there's like lots of lots
of lots of human things happening for
you so I just appreciate the work you're
doing technology for it yeah thank you
guys has been a really interesting
conversation so thank you for taking
into areas that I wasn't necessarily
expecting yeah